all right so I don't know if I'm gonna
be able to pull this off
but it feels like it's getting pretty
close to timeline and maybe I can so
let's give it a shot three basic ideas
the first idea has to do with something
like we should we should consider the
the order of magnitude of effort or
energy or degree of change that we are
bringing to an event that is necessary
for there to be a real change so let me
give you a concrete example let's say I
have a very heavy sphere like a boulder
it's maybe 100 or so pounds and it's in
a shallow pool some kind of common
concrete pool that's maybe six feet deep
and I want to get it out of the pool
right now if I if I push it for four
feet and then I let go it's gonna roll
back into the bottom of the pool if I
apply 80 pounds of force it's not going
to move at all all right so what I have
to do is I have to say I have to apply
more than a hundred pounds of force and
more than over six feet there's probably
some specific physics that describe what
happens I'm going up the curve and
friction and things like that
but unless I do at least that much then
it doesn't get out of the pool right I
get up to the goo that some amount or
not at all and it will roll back to
where it came from so that's the core
concept right the idea that if you've
got some some amount of change that is
necessary to accomplish I'm going to
call it a real change then you can you
can be quite sure that if you don't
impart a an adequate amount and by the
way inadequate directionality if I have
my whatever six hundred foot pounds of
force and I sort of do it in a circle
around the basin around the pool
it still doesn't get out right I have to
have a directionality and a magnitude
I'm wasting my time and okay that's
that's the first concept that wasn't
that hard let me say it a slightly
different way to just make sure it lands
so now what I have is I have a
a train the train is is on the tracks
and is heading for something that's very
valuable like you know the classic scene
of the you know the child who's stuck on
the track and I am a superhero and I'm
tried to stop the train well it's not
that hard to sort of say if the Train
has whatever one Giga ton of force
heading down the tracks if I want to
stop the train I have to apply at least
minus 1 or 1 Giga ton of force go in the
other direction to stop the train if I
if I apply 500 megatons
I slowed the train down and it still
kills the kid all right so that's that's
it that kind of a notion is simple right
it's a simple idea and yet often times I
think we find ourselves wasting our time
or these not accomplishing our
objectives because we don't conceive of
the order of magnitude of what needs to
be brought and to a lesser extent its
directionality before we go about trying
to do things ok - a little harder this
is also obviously fraught with
complexity and in nuanced detail so here
I have the broad brush and the broad
brush is something like okay what's the
order of magnitude that we're dealing
with
how big a challenge are we dealing with
right now if we want to affect a real
change or at least if we want to you
know save the kid on the tracks what do
we need to accomplish well what kind of
energy do we need to bring to bear
so to maybe just do a little bit of
double-clicking we can take some
examples so one example might be the
implications of cell phones and social
media technology in the context of
capitalism right so the competition and
and Metcalfe's law right the dynamic
that the more things attract them were
viable they get which creates lock-in
effects and the interface between
Metcalfe's law and capitalism or Locke
and effects generate huge amounts of
flows of money which generate more
capacity to maintain the integrity and
the existence of the thing that has
locked in so it's being maintained
through two dimensions
combine that with say for example
sophisticated advances in cognitive
science and in artificial intelligence
and the you know the competitive
landscape is attention to generate the
results that my friend Tristan Harris
has been continually bringing up which
is that we were becoming more and more
progressively addicted in particular our
kids are becoming more and more
progressively addicted to mobile social
media Facebook snapchat etc and that
when you kind of dig into the
consequences at the level of neurology
at the node level of like losing the
capacity to even have a sense of self
and self esteem outside of these weird
social signaling dynamics the
consequences are in fact really
significantly catastrophic so there's a
train called this big complex of
capitalism and technology and Metcalfe's
law and cognitive science and our
inability to inhibit ourselves from
strip-mining our cognitive psychology
and the generation of kids on a global
basis that are being run over by it all
right so that's one I can Heather how
about the the the dynamic between the
the hyper polarized environment the
degree to which that hyper polarized
environment takes any particular problem
let's say for example this question of
when whether when and how to wear masks
or whether when and how to have vaccines
and takes what is in some sense a
technical problem or at least can be
addressed meaningfully as a technical
problem but converts it into a political
problem and then converts it into a
hyper polarized political problem in the
context of a real event some kind of
virus pandemic which by the way if you
flag there's no virus or you flag people
who said there's no virus or idiots
either one of those your evidencing the
hyperpolarization piece and has
implications for each choice that we
make around this particular event
generates things like giant global
depressions which generate things like
giant global social unrest okay that's
another big problem by the way the
trajectory of that big problem is
potentially the extinction of the human
race all right the species in general
might go away as we kind of let that
train move down the tracks and we can do
this over and over again we can do it in
the context of you know Daniels phrase
the rivals game theoretics in the
context of accelerating technology is
inexorably self terminating when it's a
nice little pity phrase we can do it in
the context of you know the implications
of without massive technology and
rapacious competition in our environment
you know fill in the blank
long story short big train lots of kids
short track what's the order of
magnitude well I'm increasing of the
opinion that a good metaphor a good way
of getting a sense of it is this period
of time in the in in the West in Europe
around the 1500s all right the period of
time where you had the the 30 Years War
period of time where you had the
emergence of science where you had you
know the discovery of the new world and
all the implications of that from the
point of view of the West where you had
the breakdown of the feudal system and
the emergence of the capitalist system
like all these things were happening
coterminous lee and and by the way
coalesced to self-reinforcing lots of
complex ways but that's a that's a
magnitude of chain try that's a order of
magnitudes it's substantially bigger for
example than the civil rights movement
if you say the civil rights movement was
kind of a category one and I don't know
the the Civil War was maybe a category
three and the Revolutionary War is a
category four maybe this is a category
five in an order of magnitude so what I
would propose is that the the training
that we are dealing with the the
challenge that we are faced with is of
that order of magnitude and therefore
the solution to the problem must be of
that order of magnitude or larger and
anything that is of a smaller order of
magnitude is either a waste of time or
could be a tactical way of
buying US time which is fine like we
need as much time as we can get all
right three this is this is maybe
working how the do we pull that off
so here I'm just so going to propose
something this is my suggestion on how
we can solve that problem and there's
something about the the mode of the
suggestion that is part of the
suggestion itself which is to say that
if you don't understand at all what I'm
about to say that's kind of okay because
part of the point is that there's
certain people who are or at least in my
proposal in my proposition I'm always
talking to a couple of folks here maybe
self a million but not the whole
population and and that groups job is to
do a hell of a lot better job than I'm
doing and to bring in more okay so the
proposition is something like this big
hairy complex problems require a
different kind of mind a different kind
of consciousness I've referred to this
variously as collective intelligence and
distributed cognition other people talk
about it differently
the guy who read recently enticed anil
kapoor a-- talks about it in terms of
indigenous knowing and it just knowing
intrinsically works in the context of
distributed cognition lots of minds
involved in very specific ways the human
consciousness the human mind developed
in the context of of an obligate group
we are we are not individuals in any
meaningful sense right we are always
members of some group and infecting a
pretty large group like that dunbar
notion of 150 people seems pretty
fundamental all right so we we fit into
a context that has a large number of
people and here's the thing we're not
all the same and we're very much not
interchangeable like we we each are well
suited to some subset of the different
basic roles that are
look at our necessary for the well
functioning of the human trial okay so
the notion is something like this this
is a bit of a journey but here to follow
me on this the thing we have to do is we
have to actually reach rival eyes and I
don't mean that in the stupid sense I
mean that in a much more nuanced sense
we tend to do something else
we like simulated tribes and that's a
mess we have to actually find a way to
actually retry by like really Rico here
with a richly connected the word
coherence is crucians like the key the
point here richly connected group that
contains all of the different subtypes
of humaneness that we need so we're
robbing at tribal and in that context to
become retried alized
means recovering recreating tribal like
relationships and this means for example
rediscovering some of the more
fundamental roles in that context and
the one of them to bring out
specifically right now to one is
something like shaman the other is
something like say elder or chief or
something like that and obviously at
this point the language is going to be
very sketchy we could play slightly
differently one role has to do with the
capacity and responsibility for engaging
in the thing that tyson refers to as
turn around or turn about other people
like forest land ii think talk about
this concept of transcendent design and
without what I would say is something
like the ability to perceive the
transcendent operator the generator
function the highly abstract perceive it
well like actually be able to operate in
that mode and then to be able to support
that into a capacity to be actualized
and that when I say this shamanic type I
kind of that's what I mean that function
that capacity and then there's another
capacity ended by the with many of
course but there's another capacity
which has to do with something like
representing the embodied whole my
thinking this is leadership individual
who cannot help but prioritize the
well-being of the whole tribe over
themselves or any distinct individual
and in whom that fact is has a felt
reality in the other members of the
tribe so there's a sense of representing
the whole in this individual so I'll use
that to describe the the chief for the
king or the leader or the queen in that
function okay so the move is something
like this the what the how and the who
are many ways co-creating so at some
level there's a way to articulate a what
at a level of abstraction that is too
high an abstraction to be perceived by
most people and is therefore not useful
at that point however it can be preceded
by members of the shamanic class and
they can begin the process of
collaborating around that level of
abstraction here is a solution the at
least in principle is designed to have
both the order of magnitude and the
directionality necessary to address the
challenge that we're dealing with and
this is going to be a massive systemic
shift alright it's going to be a shift
again of the order of magnitude of you
know the 15th and 16th centuries then
that who begins to have enough
completeness and enough clarity and
perhaps quality of expression to begin
bringing in this next category of who
and these these chieftains these Queens
who have hopefully an ability to also
perceive that probably at a more
embodied way but in whom is vested the
responsibility and the capacity to
generate coherence among the people and
among the the body of the whole
whole the tribe the rest of the people
and then there's a collaboration between
the shamanic type and the chieftain type
in increasingly more richly articulating
the what and then increasingly more
fully embodying the what into into house
I the chieftain category is going to
have a fastest superior capacity both to
articulate and to execute on but how
then we start bringing in other types
right there are key elements this other
type ologies that have capacities to do
things like implementation and strategy
and maintaining integrity and conflict
resolution and all the other stuff
that's part of human II and so there's a
recovery of a fundamental topology of
the human tribe that has the capacity to
contemplate the order of magnitude of
complexity and intensity and
directionality necessary to address the
fundamental problem which has a
progressive process where the more the
who is real the more the what becomes
real which increases the capacity to
attract and orient a more real who and
you start getting a positive feedback
loop until the house starts showing up
and then and then it's done okay now I
warned you that's pretty darn abstract I
myself can can prefer or I can generate
instantiations of the abstraction in the
practical but they're not right they're
not good enough they're not rich enough
they're useful as examples to orient
people and help them begin to sort of in
themselves oh right okay that kind of
thing I get what you're talking about
maybe more like this so the thing of
course is we need more who and when you
do it pretty quickly which is the point
of this series